In this lesson, we're going to be talking about object types in TypeScript.
Objects are everywhere in JavaScript and TypeScript, so having an understanding how to
type them is critical skill for writing safe, maintainable code.
In TypeScript, an object type describes the shape of an object, what property it has,
and what types those properties should be.
So we have properties, property types, and whether they're required versus optional.
Unlike JavaScript, TypeScript lets us be very explicit about object structure.
So let's have an example of that, and we define its shape as follows.
We define some properties, say name, and a type, object string, and maybe an age property
of type number.
Now what we can do is we can initialize that object with the actual values by doing
equal sign, then curly braces, and then we can specify the actual values, say name, that
can be Alice, and the age, we can set for example to 30.
Notice we put semicolons after the definition, but commas on the actual values.
So here we define an object type in line.
The object must have a name, that's a string, and an age, that is a number.
If we miss a property or use a wrong type, then TypeScript's going to immediately show us
an error.
So if we change an age, for example, and put some speech marks, it's going to, we hover
over it, it's going to show us that we have made a mistake.
Let's just change it back to a number.
Now object types prevent a huge class of bugs, they catch our mistakes before our code runs.
And this is especially important when working with things like APIs and large objects.
But sometimes not all object properties are acquired.
Let's say for example that the age is an optional field, we can do that by putting a
question mark at the end, and then we can actually move the property here and TypeScript's
going to be happy.
But sometimes you also want properties that cannot be changed after creation.
Let's say we define an ID property, and we can do that by ID and then a number.
So that's going to make us enter in ID, which we can do by ID one, that keeps TypeScript
happy.
But let's say we don't want to change the ID at all.
We can do that by doing the read only here.
That means when we come to here, and we say for example user, let me specify the ID.
Then if we try and change it to two, it's not going to let us because it's a read only
property.
Now often objects can also contain other objects.
Let me show an example of that.
Let's do an object of order.
And the order is going to have a few properties, but most importantly we're going to create
an object inside it of type customer.
Let's have a customer, and the customer is going to have a name property of string, and
an email address, and the order ID, let's put on here is a number.
We can see we have an ID property on our main order object, and we also have this embedded
object with a name and an email address for a customer.
Now we can actually create that object by to equal sign, then curly brace, we can do
ID, let's say 101, and then we can set up our customer, so bits of by the name, let's
say Alice again, let's get an email address, just say up test at test.com.
Type script enforces structure at every single level, even deeply nested objects.
The objects can also contain arrays as well, so let's do an example of that.
Let's remove this, and let's create a blog post object, blog post, and we're going to
give it a title, obviously string, and also some tags, and the tag are going to be in
array of strings, which we do by doing some square brackets.
Now we can create this object, let's give it a title and say my title, and all the tags
themselves, we do that inside the square brackets, then we can say Type script and programming,
for example.
So this ensures every element in the array follows this correct type, you might be thinking
why bother with all this at all, why not just use the object type from JavaScript, and
let me show you what's happening.
So if we do, let's say let's put a value, set it to object, now we can do value equals,
let's say we set a the object to name, and Alice, what we can now do is to value equals,
we can set it to an array, for example.
The Type Scripts not going to complain, and it's not giving us any protection at all,
so the object just means it's not a primitive, and it's not describing any structure.
So you want to avoid using this object pretty much all costs, in other ways you're to
fit in the whole purpose of using the Type Script.
Now when we're using Type Scripts, our objects types can get quite large, in line
definitions, it can often become quite messy.
So let's go back and we're going to, this time, create our user, or define our user type,
but we're going to use the actual type alias, which we can do by doing type, and then
user, and now we can do our actual property, so ID number, let's say name, string, email,
I can spell it, email string.
Now this type gives us the option to reuse this object type anyway we want, so we could
do const, user one, we can now say this is our type user, now we can define the properties,
ID one, name, that is, and you also need the email address of course, and it's @test.com.
And again, we can come in and we can create another user, we can do const, user, two
equals, user, for example, and then define its properties.
Let's have a look at a more realistic API example, perhaps that's to find a type for an
API response, we can do type, API response, let's give it a status of number, and we're
going to now create an inline object to the data, and this is going to have an ID of number,
and a title of string.
This is going to make our API responses are predictable, and much safer to work with.
In summary, our object types allows us to describe the shape of objects, and they also
allow us to enforce, required, and any optional properties, as well as improving safety and